Rico Lebrun Collection
Rico Lebrun Collection
1932-1983
1932-1964
Lebrun, Rico, 1900-1964.
0.75 linear ft.
Italian-born painter and sculptor. Collection includes correspondence, memorabilia, and writings both by Lebrun and related to his life and works.
2745164
Biographical History
Rico (Federico) Lebrun (1900-1964) was an Italian-born American painter, muralist, illustrator and sculptor.
Born in Naples, he was educated at the National Technical School and the National Technical Institute in Italy. Beginning his career as a stained-glass window designer in Naples, the company was eventually purchased by an American company, the Pittsburgh Plate Glass Factory, which offered Lebrun a one-year position in Illinois, prompting his move to the United States. Moving to New York for several years after finishing the job in Illinois, Lebrun worked as a fashion illustrator before returning to Italy to receive a more in-depth art education, focusing on frescoes. Returning then to the United States, he was commissioned for such works as a mural for the New York City Post Office Annex (no longer extant), and worked in 1940 for Walt Disney Studios as a lecturer.
Over the course of his career, Lebrun taught at many universities as a guest lecturer, including at such institutions as Tulane and Yale. In the 1950s, he turned his attention to the subject matter of the Crucifixion, eventually creating a triptych depicting the scene. Continuing the Biblical theme, he created a mural on the theme of Genesis at Pomona College in California, which still exists today. Receiving many honors throughout his career, including the Merit Medal of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences, Lebrun was nonetheless somewhat obscure throughout his life, due to his unconformity with contemporary movements, such as abstract art. Spending his last years in California, he died in Malibu at the age of 63.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Rico Lebrun Collection consists of correspondence, memorabilia related to Lebrun and his works, and Lebrun's writings.
Correspondence consists of letters sent by Lebrun, primarily to Leonard Rubenstein and to Sheila Hicks, as well as his correspondence with the Pittsburgh International Exhibition.
Memorabilia contains documents relating to Lebrun's life and works, particularly his paintings Genesis and Crucifixion, as well as obituaries and other biographical material.
Writings contains miscellaneous materials by Lebrun regarding specific artists, genres of art, and his own background and art philosophy.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is divided into three series, with each series arranged alphabetically.
Related Material
Syracuse University Art Galleries owns a number of Lebrun pieces, including his Crucifixion, which is on display in the Heroy Geology building.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Illustrators; Art -- Painters; Art -- Sculptors; Lebrun, Rico, 1900-1964.; Illustrators -- United States -- 20th century.; Painters -- United States -- 20th century.; Sculptors -- United States -- 20th century.; Mural painting and decoration -- United States -- 20th century.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Exhibition catalogs.; Typescripts.; Transcripts.; Notes (documents); Sound recordings.; Tape reels.; Painters.; Sculptors.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gifts, various, 1967-1979.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - To Hicks, Sheila, 1962-1966 (Box 1)
  - Pittsburgh International Exhibition, 1951-1955; regarding Lebrun serving on the show jury (Box 1)
  - To Rubenstein, Lewis, 1932-1963; 2 folders; some items in Italian (Box 1)
  - Other, 1941-1965 (Box 1)
- Memorabilia
  - Clippings, 1956-1964; articles about Lebrun's work and his death (Box 1)
  - College Art Journal, XVII, 1, 1957; includes article about Lebrun's Crucifixion (Box 1)
  - Current Biography, vol. 13, no. 8, 1952; includes Lebrun (Box 1)
  - Drawings brochure, 1961; promoting the book, Rico Lebrun: Drawings (Box 1)
  - Exhibit materials, 1967-1983; postcard (1967) and exhibit book (1983) (Box 1)
  - Genesis mural, 1960-1962; 3 folders; magazines, clippings, and other materials (Box 1)
  - In Memoriam: Rico Lebrun, 1964; program (Box 1)
  - Negatives, undated; unidentified Lebrun painting (Box 1)
  - Report on Lebrun fresco, 1941 (Box 1)
  - A salute to Rico Lebrun, 1961; article by Julio Gonzalez Tejada (Box 1)
  - Sketch, undated; with document describing measurements (Box 1)
  - A Talk with Rico Lebrun [The Vision of the Artist with William D. Gorman], May 1963; lebrun_r_001; Program 34 of more than 1000 done by the Center for the Study of Democratic Institutions (CSDI); 1/4 inch audio tape; running time 40:00 (Box 2)
  - A Talk with Rico Lebrun, transcript, 1962; transcript of above (Box 1)
- Writings
  - Fragment, undated (Box 1)
  - Notes on artists, circa 1936-1937; some in Italian (Box 1)
  - Notes on frescoes, undated (Box 1)
  - "On art", undated; 3 folders; typescript (Box 1)
  - "Statement by the artist", undated; typescript (Box 1)